Today I'm going to show you an
alternative method to making delicious
strawberry gelato.
Yep, you can make delicious gelato and
ice cream with store-bought jams,
jellies, and marmalades. And there's one
important thing that you need to account
for, and that's the sugars and the
solids. So, let's get an ice cream
calculator up, and I'll show you how to
add those to your system. With our ice
cream calculator up, this is a different
ice cream calculator. This is a
Chromebased web app. I will put a link
in the description. It's made by the
same person that you made the original
ice cream calculator, but it made it a
bit more accessible to those that are on
Macs. He's also done a total web- based
solution as well for those that don't
use Chrome as a browser, but I'll go
through that another day. So, we're
going to add our jam. Now, this is a
pure strawberry jam, and we're going to
look at our ingredient database. Okay,
this is kind of what we're we're working
for. I've actually added this already,
but as you can see, because I'm not
logged in, it doesn't show it up. So,
I'm going to quickly log in. And here is
our ingredients library as well. So, if
I type in jam now, you can see I've put
this in here. But if we want to add a
new ingredient such as our jam, we can
click add new, give it a name,
strawberry jam.
And here we go down to our composition.
Now on the back of the ingredients, you
can see here it's got sugars, gluc which
is glucose and fructose and standard
sugar, strawberries, citric acid, and
pectin. Now, of all of the ingredients,
it's just really the sugars that we need
to account for. The strawberries, we got
no idea how much they put in here. And
there's actually no way to tell, but the
sugars are what are going to change our
recipe. It's what's going to make our
ice cream or gelato freeze properly or
incorrectly and make it super icy. For
the nutritional facts, it's per 50
milliliters, 1 tbspoon. We have 10 gram
of sugar, which equates to 10
milliliters of sugar. So, let's just
convert everything to grams for ease. 15
grams, 10 grams. So that's 23 of that is
sugar. All right. So what we have here
is
our list of ingredients down here.
Sugars, total sugars. So 2/3 of 100%
because if we go up here, it's per 100
g. Okay, so let's just make that 100%.
It's much easier way to figure that out.
We can go down here. We know that 2/3 of
our total amount, so per 100 gram, is
sugar. 66.66.
Whoops. But we do know that if 66% is
solids, so sugars, that means that 34%
is water.
Now, our pack and our pod, this is a
really clever thing that this calculator
can do if you're adding a new
ingredient, is you can click on this
here where it says calculate pack and
pod for sugar from sugar composition.
So, it's not 100% accurate, but it's
really close. So, we can click on that
and we go down here and we know we've
got 10 gram, so 2/3 66% sugars. We know
that those sugars are glucose, fructose,
and sugar, but we don't know what
composition they are. We do know that
fructose is incredibly sweet. So, let's
let's do a 50/50 of fructose
and glucose. So, 33% would be glucose,
33% fructose. don't know about the
sugars but we what we can do is
calculate this basic idea of what this
jam would do to our recipe. So we can
click on okay and there it is. We can
click enter. But that tells us how we
can easily add something like a jam to
our ingredients list. So now let's
create a recipe. We're going to create a
new recipe and we're going to call it
strawberry dark chocolate because that's
what we're going to make.
And here we go. We're going to make this
a gelato. So that's staying the same. So
let's look at our ingredients.
We need milk. We're going to use whole
milk. We need cream. We're going to use
33% cream. We're going to add sugar on
here because we don't know what the
composition of our jam is going to give
our recipe. So, we're going to do that.
And finally, skim milk powder
and
a stabilizer of some kind. So, here, add
all. So, you got five ingredients
selected. Add all. And here they are by
amount. It defaults to 100 grams of
each, which we know is just insane. As
we start adding our ingredients, we can
see the levels change here. But we know
that our sugar is not going to be 100
grams because we're going to add in our
jam. All right. So, let's just pick one
of our jams. Let's just pick this one.
All right. And add it in here.
Strawberry jam.
If we add 100 grams of our strawberry
jam, our serving temperature is -3.5
approximately because we don't know what
the sugar makeup of this jam is. So,
that's pretty decent. But we can make it
stronger. And here we go. We're starting
to affect our sugars. Highlights. Our
sugars are too high. So, we can start
bringing down these kind of things
we're getting down. So, let's just get
rid of that normal sugar completely.
Look, we got 200 g worth of our
strawberry jam. So, we've got a decent
amount of water. It's bordering a little
bit too high. Our fat is at 5.05%.
So, let me play with this for 5 minutes
and then we'll come back and see where
we're at. So, here we go. We've got our
numbers. We got 200 g of our jam, 43 g
of our skim milk powder, 520 g of our
milk, 50 g of plain sugar, 185 g of
cream, and 3 g of stabilizer. This gives
us a gelato temperature of -14.4,
serving temperature, a little bit lower.
But our freezing point is is back to
about minus4
Celsius, which is perfect. Now, if you
look here, this serving temperature is
pretty much where your freezer is going
to be. Most home freezers are -17 to -20
Celsius. So, you know, 0 Fahrenheit, a
little bit lower. And that's perfect
because this means this is going to
scoop just perfectly straight out the
freezer. All right. So, another way to
do it is rather than input the numbers
yourself, you can click balance, and it
will automatically attempt to balance
your recipe. It has mixed results, but
it it's good in a pinch if you're new to
this kind of ice cream calculator. There
we go. This is our gelato, strawberry
gelato made with our storebought
strawberry jam. Let's get all those
items out and ready to go.
Right. So, we're going to start with our
milk, 777 g. Into that goes our cream,
278 g. Into that, we're going to put our
strawberry jam, 300 g.
Now, we're going to weigh out our sugar,
which is 74 g, I think. 74.9. So, 75 g.
And into that we're going to put our
stabilizer. We're going to use 4 g of
stabilizer in this. 4 g because it's
gelato. Gelato is lower fat, so it needs
much more stabilizer to make it balanced
and creamy and delicious.
We're just going to tiny whisk our
stabilizer in with that little bit of
sugar.
And that's going to go into our base as
well.
Finally,
that strawberry jam is not going to make
this super red. It's going to make this
like a really weird off pinky color. I'm
going to add some red food coloring.
This is gel food coloring. It's just
going to make it a a more attractive
color. I'm not going to go too mad with
it, but I'm just going to add enough to
make it look a little bit special.
Obviously, if you're going to use food
coloring, use one that dissolves in fat,
cuz obviously we're making ice cream,
which has got fat in it. So, that is
everything. We're going to get this on
the hob, heat this up. This stabilizer
is a warm process stabilizer. So, need
to come to 80 to 85 C. And we're going
to keep it there for 2 to 5 minutes to
fully hydrate. Then, we're going to come
back and finish this off.
Right. There we go. We're up to
temperature now. I made three variations
of this and the one that had the skin
milk powder added after the heating
phase turned out just better than the
others. I don't know why. Shouldn't make
any difference, but that's what we're
going to do now.
plenty of heat in that mix to dissolve
our skim milk powder into our base. So,
we're just going to stir this for a
minute or two and we're going to strain
that to get any pieces of that
strawberry jam out. I want this a nice
clean gelato. This is now going to cool
down. If you want to call it in an ice
bath, then by all means, just chill it
down, stir it as you go. But I'm going
to pop this in the fridge to rest
overnight and we'll come back tomorrow
and deal with the rest. So, after your
ice cream is chilled in the fridge,
we're going to take it out and bring it
back together before popping it into our
pre- chilled ice cream machine. So, it
goes just above the bottom of that top
dasher there. We're going to take some
dark chocolate. This is 60 65%. And some
nice quality olive oil. Tastes really
good. We're going to chop up our
chocolate and get it in a microwave
proof container. Put in a drop of olive
oil. This one's a much better size. And
we're going to melt that in 30 secondond
blast. I think this took about a minute,
minute and a half, something like that.
Do not burn it. Once it's all completely
stirred together, you're going to put
that aside. You can use magic shell if
you want. Doesn't taste as good. Towards
the end of the churn, you can start
drizzling that chocolate in. It will
freeze on impact and create this
beautiful stretchy tella. Once you load
up your ice cream into a container, get
it smooth on top if you can, and then
pour on top some more of that delicious
dark chocolate. Close that tub, pop it
in the freezer. I'm looking forward to
this.
Outside today, it is -31
C. And with wind chill, -40 C. Yeah,
super cold this morning, but um I mean,
you kind of get used to it. We had a
really good spell for for winter. It was
pretty mild and then my buddy and I were
saying that it's like unlikely to get
super cold again. And then five days
later, bang, hit with minus 40. Anyway,
let's try this delicious gelato.
Loving
the aesthetic of this.
That is so good.
Really, really nice.
Delicious strawberry flavor. That jam
flavor comes through nicely.
Now, one thing that concerned me
slightly was the pectin in the jam.
Unknown amount. So, we kind of had to
guess. Same way that we guess with the
the glucose and the fructose.
Strawberries naturally have a glucose
and fructose in them. So, whether it's
that, whether it's added, I I got no
idea. So, we have to take a bit of a
guess as to balancing a recipe like this
out. Turned out perfectly. and the
Stratella with that dark chocolate. This
is I think a 65% maybe a 60% dark
chocolate. It's a lint dark chocolate. I
use this on my chocolate channel. It's
amazing chocolate. Use any chocolate you
can get hold of. And you can also, like
I showed you earlier, used a magic shell
in a bottle at a pinch. Tastes like crap
compared to real chocolate, but will do
the job. Beautiful color as you can see.
And there's loads of that dark chocolate
stratechella in there as well, topped
with some of those pieces of that real
kova chocolate as well. Really makes
this stand out as a flavor. If you're
making ice cream commercially, you know,
using jam as a flavor element for an ice
cream. There are so many different jams,
jellies, and marmalades available. You
kind of, you know, make it however you
want, but you do have to make sure
that's balanced correctly. But there we
have delicious strawberry gelato made in
a really easy, simple way. You can use
any flavor, jams, jellies or mammal.
Balance it with the right amount of
sugar. Use a calculator. If you're
unsure, pop me a question in the
comments and I will help you out. But I
hope you enjoyed this one. Really nice.
I made a goodiz batches, one and a half
kilo batch. So that's two ninja creamy
deluxes, three standard ninja creamies
or a good churn batch. Good overrun on
this as well. So hope you enjoyed this
video. Don't forget to like and
subscribe and I will see you
next week.